Guide to the Heinrich Ries papers, 1889-1951.
Ries, Heinrich papers, 1889-1951.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Heinrich Ries papers, 1889-1951.
14-15-691
Heinrich Ries, 1871-1951.
1.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, diaries, minutes, notes, memoranda, reports, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence and other papers relating to Ries' career as professor of geology at Cornell University.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Heinrich Ries was professor of geology at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Mainly personal and professional correspondence, especially concerning Cornell Geology Department administration and conflicts; correspondents include Henry Platt Cushing, Edmund Ezra Day, Livingston Farrand, Adam C. Gill, Gilbert D. Harris, Charles W. Merriam, Charles S. Prosser, Floyd K. Richtmyer, Ralph S. Tarr, Oscar D. von Engeln, Henry Shaler Williams, and others. Also, one diary kept by Ries (ca. 1914-1939) and one by Henry S. Williams (1889-1892, 1904-1908) concerning departmental affairs, typescript departmental minutes (1904-1914), laboratory notes (1904-1909), memoranda, enrollment statistics, reports, notes, condolence letters, and other items relating to Ries, Williams, and the Geology Department at Cornell University.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ries, Heinrich, 1871-1951.; Cushing, Henry Platt.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Engeln, O. D. von (Oscar Diedrich), 1880-1965.; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939.; Gill, Adam C.; Harris, Gilbert D.; Merriam, Charles Warren, 1905-; Prosser, Charles S.; Richtmyer, F.K. (Floyd Karker), 1881-1939.; Tarr, Ralph S. (Ralph Stockman), 1864-1912.; Williams, Henry Shaler.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Geology Dept.; Cornell University. Geology Dept.--Administration.
Subjects:
College teachers.; Geologists.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Related collection: Mary Eleanor Davis. Student Notebooks, #37-5-1244.
Related collection: Donald T. Ries. Papers, #1350.
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence
  - B, Nov. 26, 1919-Dec. 20, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, Jan. 2, 1925-Jan. 8, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Berthiaume, Sheridan A., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, July 30, 1920-Oct. 27, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - C, Nov. 14, 1921-Mar. 9, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - C, Mar. 13, 1922-Apr. 19, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C, Apr. 23, 1923-Jan. 6, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carnegie Institution Committee, Dec. 18, 1902-Nov. 20, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Caster, Kenneth E., 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - D, Mar. 25, 1921-Dec. 6, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - E, Sept. 22, 1921-Jan. 11, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - E, Jan. 6, 1992-Apr. 1, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - E, Apr. 17, 1922-Jan. 7, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - F, Jan. 12, 1921-June 22, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - F, June 26, 1922-Sept. 24, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - G, Aug. 1, 1920-Apr. 12, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - G, Apr. 13, 1922-Nov. 26, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gill's successor and retirement, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - H, July 27, 1921-Feb. 18, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - H, Feb. 18, 1922-June 15, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - H, June 19, 1922-Sept. 30, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Harris, G.D., 1913-1916 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Harris, G.D., 1917-1934 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Harris, G.D., 1917-1935 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Harris successor, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Heckscher, 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Heroy, William B., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - I, Sept. 3, 1921-June 5, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - J, Sept. 26, 1921-Sept. 13, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - K, Sept. 6, 1921-Sept. 13, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - L, Sept. 2, 1921-Mar. 2, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - L, Mar. 6, 1922-Jan. 5, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - M, July 8, 1921-Jan. 24, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - M, Jan. 27, 1922-May 23, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - M, May 25, 1922-Jan. 6, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Merriam, Charles W., 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Millward, Louis G., 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - N, July 25, 1921-June 16, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - N, Oct. 24, 1923-May 15, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - O, Oct. 6, 1921-Oct. 30, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letters to Ogden, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Ogden, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Ogden, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - P, Sept. 9, 1921-Feb. 6, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - P, Feb. 9, 1922-May 13, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - P, May 13, 1922-Jan. 9, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - R, Aug. 3, 1921-Oct. 27, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - R, Jan. 2, 1922-Dec. 22, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - R, Jan. 5, 1923-July 1, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Richtmyer, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - S, June 21, 1921-Dec. 23, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - S, Jan. 5, 1922-Apr. 14, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - S, Apr. 18, 1922-May 9, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - S, May 9, 1922-June 9, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - S, June 16, 1922-Oct. 1, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - T, Apr. 18, 1921-Oct. 24, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - T, Oct. 26, 1921-Mar. 3, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - T, Mar. 7, 1922-May 13, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - T, May 15, 1922-Feb. 3, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - T, Feb. 5, 1923-Dec. 16, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Tucker, Helen, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - U, Oct. 18, 1921-May 22, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - V, Dec. 22, 1921-Oct. 27, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - von Engeln, 1928-1937 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - W, Aug. 2, 1921-Dec. 27, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - W, Jan. 6, 1922-Mar. 13, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - W, Mar. 15, 1922-Sept. 4, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - W, Sept. 14, 1922-Dec. 15, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - W, Jan. 3, 1923-Mar. 30, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - W, Apr. 4, 1923-Nov. 30, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - W, Dec. 4, 1923-Nov. 8, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - W, Nov. 17, 1924-Jan. 14, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Williams Fund, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Department Correspondence, 1902-1905 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Geology Correspondence, 1905-1914 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Old Cornell University letters, 1905-1931 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Assistant Professor, May 5, 1922-May 23, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Assistant Professor, May 23, 1922-June 25, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Department, 1933-1945 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Department, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Department, 1936, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Department, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Letters of condolence from former graduate students and other associates, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 83)
- Records
  - Department: records of past troubles, c. 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Chairman's Report, 1913-1921 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Geology notes: Colorado, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Department notes, c. 1939-? (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Grades in Arts, 1914-1924 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Budget, 1914-1924 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Department, 1919-1921, 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Attendance, 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chairman's Reports, 1923-1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Geology Miscellaneous, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Summer Session, 1926-1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Department meetings and business, 1928-1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Department of Geology: general, 1928-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Department, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Attendance, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - G. 100, 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Attendance, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Mineralogy, 1930-1936 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Department, 1930-1936 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Department, 1930-1937 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Annual Report, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Annual Reports to Dean, 1932-1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Department, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Department Troubles, c. 1937-1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rowland Case, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Geology Department (notebook): H.S. Williams, Department Matters, 1907-1910? (Box 3, Folder 4-8)
  - H.S. Williams memoranda, 1889-1908 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Geology Department minutes; Geological Conferences minutes, 1904-1914 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Minutes of meeting at which U.D. proposed an all-year course, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Geology Department register, 1868-1947 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Geology Department Newsletter, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 11)